A Guide to the Robert Green Ingersoll Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7025-a
Robert Green Ingersoll Collection 1877-1899
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7025-a
21 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit, 1964 November 17
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Essay on Religion, 189[?]; AMsS, 13 p.
    [States that religious sincerity is no guarantee against being deceitful, providing numerous examples of liars from the Bible, Jehovah not excluded. Includes two pages of typescript from the essay.]
  - Essay: "Has religion civilised the world?", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
    [Argues against Christianity, claiming Christians do not turn the other cheek but rather have developed many sophisticated weapons.]
  - Essay on Religion, n.d.; TMs, 2 p.
    [Argues that lying and falsehood are essential to orthodox religion.]
- Letters
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to James W. Taylor, 1877 Dec 26; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks him for sending him the remarks of the Reverend A. Palmer which were stolen from his Steinway Hall speech; and calls Palmer a dishonest man.]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to Clark Mills, 1881 May 12; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sends condolences on the occasion of the death of Mills' father.]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to Mr. Hutchins, 1884; ALS, 2 p.
    [Offers his condolence.]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to the Editor of the Herald, 1884 Dec 11; ALS, 3 p.
    [Denies that he copied his lecture on "The Mistakes of Moses" from a work by John Sherzer Hittel and offers a one thousand dollar reward to anyone who can prove it.]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to Mr. Raymond, 1889 Feb 20; ALS, 2 p.
    [Mentions Judge John J. Brady and his gratitude for an invitation to dine with the Insurance Men.]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to Major James B. Pond, 1890 Oct 23; ALS, 2 p.
    [Asks Pond to advise Baron Harden-Hickey, an expert on Indian matters who was introduced to Ingersoll by Edgar Fawcett on the possibility of lecturing on Indian philosophy and religion.]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to "My dear Friend", 1890 Dec 14; ALS, 3 p.
    [Compliments correspondent on his new political novel (no title given).]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to [John King] Cowen, 1891 Apr 8; ALS, 2 p.
    [Promises his correspondent tickets for his lecture on Shakespeare at the Brooklyn Academy of Music. ]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to [Charles Warren] Clifford, 1891 Aug 28; ALS, 2 p.
    [Asks Clifford to call the stock-brokers together to raise money before September 15, as he cannot depend on him for a dollar.]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to [Charles Warren] Clifford, 1892 May 6; ALS, 2 p.
    [Writes concerning financial matters.]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to Mr. Deacon, 1893 Apr 6; ALS, 1 p.
    [Regrets his inability to come to the Clover Club because he wil not be in the city at that time.]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to Samuel S. McClure, 1893 Aug 10; ALS, 1 p.
    [Requests the payment of $1,000 to "Ouida," as the agreed upon price of her manuscript on "Birds."]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to J. Frank, 1894 May 12; ALS, 1 p.
    [Insists that he has never been indicted for blasphemy in Delaware or in any other state.]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to [James B.] Pond, 1897 Feb 15; ALS, 1 p.
    [Has instructed his agent to give Pond a box and regrets not receiving Pond's letter in time.]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to Raley Husted Bell, 1897 Mar 28; ALS, 4 p.
    [Has read Bell's article about himself in Bell's magazine; does not consider himself worthy of such praise but is deeply grateful; cautions Bell not to injure himself by praising him too much in Georgia. ]
  - Robert Green Ingersoll to Mr. Bloch, 1899; ALS, 2 p.
    [Returns a letter which he does not find worth answering; and promises to write something on the subject soon.]
- Miscellaneous
  - Engraved New Year's card with text by Robert Green Ingersoll, plus a calling card, n.d.; Greeting card
  - J. W. Keller to the Managing Editor of Nebraska State Journal, n.d.; Telegram
    [Keller wants Ingersoll interviewed on the prayers that were offered in Cleveland, Ohio for him but Ingersoll refuses. With ANS by William Reed Dunrey and Robert Green Ingersoll. ]